<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the distressed state of the church of Christ professing the protestant religion in the great dukedom of Lithuania, presented to the view of all compassionate Christians.</title>
            <author>Krainski, John de Kraino.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K750B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R227274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896362</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896362</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2406:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the distressed state of the church of Christ professing the protestant religion in the great dukedom of Lithuania, presented to the view of all compassionate Christians.</title>
                  <author>Krainski, John de Kraino.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed in the year of our salvation,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John de Kraino Krainski.--Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Martyrs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:154237:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <p>A RELATION OF THE <hi>DISTRESSED STATE</hi> OF THE CHURCH of
CHRIST, <hi>PROFESSING</hi> The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion in the Great
<hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>LITH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ANIA, Preſented to the view of all
Compaſſionate</hi> Chriſtians.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. XLI. 1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Bleſsed is he that conſidereth the Poor, the Lord will
deliver him in time of trouble. The Lord will preſerve him, and keep him
alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the Earth, and thou wilt not deliver
him into the Will of his Enemies.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LAMENT. III. 52, 53, 54.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Mine Enemies chaſed me ſore like a Bird, without cauſe:
They have cut off my life in the Dungeon, and caſt a Stone upon me. Waters
flowed over mine Head, then I ſaid, I am cut off.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year of our Salvation 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:154237:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lament. I. 16.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>For theſe things I weep; mine Eye, mine Eye runneth down with
water; becauſe the <hi>Comforter,</hi> that ſhould relieve my Soul, is far
from me: my <hi>Children are deſolate; becauſe the Enemy
prevailed.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <p>They have heard, that I ſigh, there is none to comfort me: all
mine <hi>Enemies</hi> have heard of my trouble, and they are glad,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi> Ibid.</hi> v. <hi>21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:154237:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Relation <hi>of the Diſtreſſed State of
the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>profeſsing the</hi> Proteſtant
<hi>Religion in the Great</hi> Dukedom <hi>of</hi> Lithuania; <hi>Preſented
to the view of all Compaſſionate</hi> Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>THE fatal and Bloody <hi>Tragedy,</hi> which, with a great deal
of Confuſion, hath been acted on the <hi>Theatre</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi>
near upon fourty years, or upwards, having daſhed moſt potent <hi>Kingdoms,
Nations,</hi> and <hi>Provinces,</hi> one againſt another, hath at laſt
(with more Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe <hi>later</hi>) reached our <hi>Sarmatian</hi>
Climate, and therein that moſt flouriſhing Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> but
eſpecially the Great <hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> and the
<hi>Provinces</hi> belonging thereunto; wherein it hath ſo ruined, and
deſtroyed many magnificent, and populous <hi>Cities,</hi> leſſer
<hi>Towns,</hi> and <hi>Villages</hi> without number; that there are not ſo
much, as any Marks left, where they ſtood before.</p>
            <p>This is now the twelfth year, ſince the higheſt, and
<hi>moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judg</hi> of all <hi>unrighteous Nations,</hi> having
baniſhed Peace from our Countrey, hath, in his fierce anger, called for many
perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, cruel, ſwift, and mighty <hi>Nations,</hi> to execute his
Judgments againſt us. And theſe, not having been in the leaſt provoked by
Us, but onely thirſting after our <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> have
waſhed their cruel hands therein, and are not ſatisfied therewith, but to
the ſpoiling of the Goods have added moſt exquiſite Torments upon the
<hi>Bodies</hi> of the true <hi>Profeſſours</hi> of
<hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 1648. when the firſt <hi>Rebellion</hi> of the
<hi>Coſſacks</hi> broke forth, to whom the <hi>Tartarians</hi> readily did
aſſociate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the <hi>Nobility</hi> was ſought out, with much
diligence, by the furious <hi>Rebels,</hi> to be ſlaughtered; and all ſuch,
as were not of the <hi>Greek Religion,</hi> were moſt ignominiouſly put to
death, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſtinction; where were many numerous
<hi>Congregations</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:154237:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->of the
<hi>Reformed Proteſtants,</hi> whoſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> were not ſpared
alſo.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Cruelty</hi> of the furious <hi>Coſſacks</hi>
was ſo barbarous, that the <hi>Tartars</hi> themſelves (though their
<hi>Aſſociates</hi>) would not be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo much Innocent Blood; but
compaſſionately did reſcue as many, as they could, out of their
hands.</p>
            <p>Many had their <hi>Skins</hi> pulled over their <hi>Ears,</hi>
whileſt they were <hi>alive.</hi> Others had their <hi>Hands,</hi> and
<hi>Feet,</hi> cut off. Some had their <hi>Bowels</hi> taken out, alive. Others
had their <hi>Shin-bones</hi> bored thorough. To ſome they poured <hi>melted
Lead</hi> in at the <hi>Wounds,</hi> which they made in their <hi>Heads,</hi>
or <hi>Bodies.</hi> Their <hi>Eyes</hi> were plucked out: there is no number of
thoſe, that were <hi>hanged.</hi> And it was accounted a <hi>great
Mercy,</hi> if any had his <hi>Head</hi> cut off with a <hi>Sword,</hi> or if
they were ſent away as <hi>perpetual Sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves</hi> to the <hi>Turk.</hi> Poor <hi>Parents,</hi> and
<hi>Husbands,</hi> were forced to look on, whileſt their <hi>Wives,</hi> and
<hi>Daughters</hi> were raviſhed.</p>
            <p>This was the miſerable Condition of our <hi>Countrey,</hi> and
<hi>Church,</hi> for ſeveral years together, during the <hi>Civil Wars.</hi>
But afterwards, when we all begun to hope for <hi>better</hi> things, there
fell a <hi>new,</hi> and more ſtrange Calamity upon us, when we were almoſt
conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before. For the perfidious <hi>Moſcov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te,</hi> having taken notice of the diſtraction, and
devaſtation, which by the juſt Hand of <hi>God</hi> befell us; and that the
ſtrength of <hi>Lithuania</hi> was, by continual <hi>Inteſtine Wars,</hi>
decayed, he preſently took an opportunity to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade it; and, to that effect,
having found out ſome <hi>Pretenſes,</hi> he came with an <hi>Army</hi> of
two hundred thouſand men, and aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to himſelf ſixty thouſand
of the Rebellious <hi>Coſsacks;</hi> who carried all before them, like a
<hi>Flood,</hi> ſpoiling, burning, deſtroying all, that they met with,
ſacking the <hi>ſtrong Holds,</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> not leaving one
Corner in all <hi>Lithuania</hi> unſearched. Never was greater
<hi>Tyrannie</hi> committed in thoſe Parts before. There was no regard of
<hi>Tears,</hi> and <hi>Lamentations:</hi> no Pity ſhewed to yielding
Perſons: all, without diſcretion, were cut to pieces. The <hi>common
Multitude</hi> were ſlaughtered out of hand; but the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and
<hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> were carried away; and, upon deliberation, were either
<hi>hanged,</hi> or <hi>burnt alive.</hi> Every Corner being filled with
<hi>Maſſacres,</hi> made the Blood run, like <hi>Streams,</hi> through the
<hi>Streets</hi> of Towns, and Cities.</p>
            <p>But the Condition of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> was moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; <pb facs="tcp:154237:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->for
as many, as were taken, were, with mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> put to ſeveral kinds
of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adrian Chylinsky,</hi> a man moſt conſpicuous both for
his <hi>old Age,</hi> as alſo for his <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi>
whereby he deſerved eminently of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
being ſurpriſed at his own houſe, had his <hi>Hands,</hi> and
<hi>Legs,</hi> tyed together, and then <hi>roſted alive,</hi> leiſurely by
degrees, there being but ſome <hi>Chips,</hi> and <hi>Straw,</hi> gathered
about him. Two of the ſame <hi>Name,</hi> a <hi>Father,</hi> and a
<hi>Son,</hi> called <hi>Smolsky,</hi> both <hi>Miniſters</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> near <hi>Vilna,</hi> the chiefeſt City in
<hi>Lithuania,</hi> had their <hi>Heads</hi> moſt cruelly ſawed off with a
<hi>Sickle.</hi> Another <hi>Miniſter,</hi> in a Town called
<hi>Holowozyn,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>Slawin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skie,</hi> had a <hi>new</hi>
Torment put upon him: for they cut him by pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo long, as he lived. Many
other <hi>Miniſters</hi> were amongſt the high <hi>Mountains</hi> expoſed
bound, and naked, to the <hi>Snow,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream cold <hi>Air;</hi> which
made their noble Souls forſake their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable <hi>Tabernacles.</hi> And
by this kind of death, this laſt <hi>Winter,</hi> there were deſtroyed
above fifteen hundred innocent Souls; who, ſeeking for ſhelter, were in
their <hi>flight</hi> over-taken. Thoſe, that were moſt <hi>healthy,</hi>
or <hi>ſtrong,</hi> were ſent away to be made <hi>Slaves;</hi> but others
were either flay'd alive, or cut into pieces. The num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, that were
thus miſerably put to death, as alſo the ſeveral kinds of
<hi>Torments,</hi> which poor innocent Creatures were put to, no
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> can deſcribe.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Juncture</hi> of <hi>Affairs,</hi> all the
<hi>Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to forſake their <hi>Dwelling-places.</hi> And
there is above fourty, of whom it is not known, what kind of death they
ſuffered: but that they are dead, is certain; becauſe they are not found,
nor were they carried into <hi>Captivity.</hi> The <hi>Churches,</hi> for the
moſt part, as far as the <hi>Enemy</hi> could reach, were deſtroyed by
<hi>Fire:</hi> All the <hi>Bells</hi> were carried away; ſo that there are
but few left in the whole <hi>Dukedom.</hi> The <hi>deſolate Fields,</hi> and
<hi>Water</hi> onely were left, as Witneſſes of the inſolency of a
<hi>barbarous Enemy;</hi> for all <hi>Dwelling-places,</hi> and <hi>Woods</hi>
were pulled, and cut down, and burnt to Aſhes.</p>
            <p>One would think, that the Land had been by this time
chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſufficiently, and that the ſharp Rod of our Correction
ſhould have been broken: but God was not yet pleaſed to put a period to our
Calamities; for every year our Countrey had a <hi>New Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:154237:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->raiſed upon it, and ſo that
little, which the <hi>former</hi> had left, the <hi>ſucceeding</hi> Enemy
devoured: For, in the year 1655, the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of our <hi>Enemies</hi> was
augmented, by the coming of the <hi>Swede:</hi> whoſe Armies, by reaſon of
the vicinity of theſe three <hi>Provinces, Boruſſia, Curland,</hi> and
<hi>Liefland,</hi> which they had in their power, have, for the ſpace of five
years, afflicted our Countrey alſo. And, without any reſpect of the
<hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> they uſed <hi>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es:</hi> and, by their coming into the Countrey, they
made us lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be more hated by thoſe of the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi>
then before; although after that all the <hi>Poliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Armies</hi> had forſaken their <hi>King,</hi> and that
His <hi>Sacred Royal Majeſty</hi> had with drawn himſelf out of His
<hi>Kingdom,</hi> by reaſon of the Power of the <hi>Enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> who preſſed all places, and being abſent
for a very long time in <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſia,</hi> yet the <hi>Lithuanian Churches,</hi> all that time,
remained ſtill conſtant, and faithful to their <hi>Gracious King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this came upon us, undoubtedly, becauſe of the
<hi>Sins</hi> of our Country: yet the <hi>Wrath</hi> of God did ſtill burn
againſt us; for, a little while after, He did ſend <hi>another</hi> Enemy,
out of <hi>another Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranſylvania;</hi> in whoſe
<hi>Army,</hi> beſides the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and
<hi>Tranſylvanians,</hi> there were <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldavians, Valachians, Servians,</hi> and other <hi>Eaſtern</hi>
Barbarous <hi>Nations,</hi> who came with great hopes, that they ſhould be
enriched with our <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and <hi>Goods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This brought a new Calamity upon that, which remained; for they
made <hi>havock</hi> of all, waſted, and deſtroyed all <hi>without
diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> The <hi>Churches,</hi> that remained, they robbed; the
<hi>Houſes</hi> rifled, and burnt; the <hi>People</hi> driven into <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſhment;</hi> and thoſe, that could
not fly, were <hi>murthered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot be ſufficiently lamented, much leſs uttered, what
in ſuch long continuance of our <hi>Troubles,</hi> amongſt ſo many
<hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtern, Western,
Northern,</hi> and other <hi>Enemies,</hi> our <hi>Native Country,</hi> the
<hi>Church,</hi> and every <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mber</hi> thereof, have ſuffered. The <hi>dead,</hi> and the
<hi>unborn,</hi> were then accounted bleſſed: the <hi>weaker Sex</hi> was
reputed as the moſt Infortunate; For we have ſeen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<hi>Illuſtrious,</hi> and <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble Families</hi> ſo exhauſted, and brought to extremitie; that
they have not had <hi>Bread</hi> to eat. We have ſeen <hi>Noble Men,</hi> and
<hi>Matrons, Virgins,</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> of great <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:154237:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->mancipated under the pleaſure, and
ſervitude of the <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vians, Tartarians, Coſſacks,</hi> and
others; under which both they, and many <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the
<hi>Goſpel</hi> to this day do groan heavily.</p>
            <p>In conſideration of thoſe <hi>Extremitis,</hi> which indeed
are <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary,</hi> we cannot but adore the juſt <hi>Judgments</hi>
of God thus poured upon us by reaſon of our <hi>Sins,</hi> and deplore our
ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: and the more by reaſon of the ſmall hopes of
Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or deliverance from ſuch a Devaſtation. For, though we are
brought very low already, having been made ſubject to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<hi>Waſtings,</hi> great <hi>Terrours,</hi> and <hi>Troubles,</hi> as having
had Death before our Eyes continually; yet there is ſtill matter of new
<hi>Troubles</hi> at home, eſpecially to thoſe, that deſire to ſerve
God in ſimplicity, and purity: to this particularly one Calamity fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
another, as the Waves, in a <hi>tempeſtuous Sea,</hi> come one upon
another.</p>
            <p>Our very <hi>Neighbours</hi> do hate, and perſecute the
<hi>Remnant</hi> of us ſtill, with as much eagerneſs, as our <hi>foreign
Enemies</hi> did: they deprive us of our <hi>Churches</hi> yet remaining:
thoſe <hi>Lands,</hi> which were given for the maintainance of
<hi>Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Scholes,</hi> they give away, as if they had been
their own: our <hi>Miniſters</hi> are baniſhed; and ſuch, as remain are
beaten, and misuſed: the Threatnings of our <hi>total Exilement</hi> are
encreaſed: In a word, all the <hi>Reformed Proteſtans</hi> are accounted as
the <hi>Off-ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the World,</hi> and the original cauſe of all the
<hi>Troubles,</hi> which are hitherto befallen to the Country. Hence it is,
that they are hated, abuſed, threatned more and more: and whatſoever may be
found <hi>odious</hi> amongſt men, all that is put upon them, for to make
their calamities the greater.</p>
            <p>We do not queſtion, but that all, that ſhall read, or hear
of theſe things, and have the leaſt <hi>ſpark</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian
Charitie</hi> left in their Hearts: or take to heart the <hi>affliction</hi> of
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> will take Compaſſion on us being affected with the truth
of that <hi>Worſhip, Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> which did
ſhine amongſt us, even in the midſt of our <hi>Troubles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>our parts,</hi> we have no other recourſe, but to the
<hi>Goodneſs</hi> of our <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>ſympathie</hi> of the
<hi>Members</hi> of his <hi>Church;</hi> and therefore, following the
<hi>Practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the 
<pb facs="tcp:154237:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
               <hi>Example</hi> of the
<hi>Churches</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate, Bohemia,</hi> and others; which being
in the ſame condition, ſome few years ago, implored the aid of their
<hi>fellow-Members</hi> of the <hi>Reformed-Proteſtant Church,</hi> we do
likewiſe make our recourſe to your <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and
<hi>Charitie.</hi> For we are perſwaded, that God hath in theſe Times made
theſe <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> more happy, and flouriſhing,
then others, that they might be a place for <hi>refuge,</hi> and a
<hi>Port</hi> of <hi>ſafety</hi> for thoſe, that ſuffer
<hi>Ship-wrack</hi> for the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Jeſus</hi> elſewhere.</p>
            <p>Look therefore, we beſeech you, upon us, as <hi>Objects</hi>
of <hi>Pitie,</hi> and for the <hi>Love of God,</hi> for the <hi>ſacred bonds
of unity</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> ſtretch forth your hands, that
the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine-yard</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> may not be utterly deſtroyed.
Send ſuitable comforts to thoſe, that are comfortleſs; ſtrengthen the
hands of the <hi>feeble;</hi> ſupport the <hi>weak,</hi> ſupply the wants
of the <hi>needy</hi> with your <hi>liberality:</hi> not doubting, but that the
<hi>Lord,</hi> who is the <hi>rewarder of all good deeds,</hi> and who takes
all the works of <hi>Charitie,</hi> beſtowed upon the <hi>Members</hi> of his
<hi>Militant Church,</hi> as if they had been beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, will
be your ſufficient reward, and at the Great day of Accounts will put you in
minde of ſuch Works for your <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> comfort. Theſe are the
prayers, and deſires of thoſe; who, in the name of all the <hi>Lithuanian
Churches,</hi> have ſent their <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to you, who
ſollicits this in <hi>their</hi> Name, as having been an
<hi>Eye-witneſs,</hi> in many places, of their diſtreſſed condition,
and partaker of their Evils.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John de Kraino Krainski,</hi> Miniſter of
God's Word, and the <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of the
<hi>Churches.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154237:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
